here's an intriguing three-dimensional
way to sum
squares start with 6 1X 1 by 1 cuboids
as shown here each of these cuboids
contains a volume of 1^ 2 * 1 so the
total volume of these six is 6 * 1
squared we can glue these six together
to form this cuboid now we can enclose
this shape using six 2x 2x1 cuboids two
on top and two on bottom and one in the
front and the back each each of these
cuboids contains a volume of 2^ 2 * 1 so
when we glue them together to form a
shell we add a volume of 6 * 2^ 2 now
let's create a new shell for this shape
by using six 3x3 by1 cuboids two on the
left and the right each and one each in
the front and the back each of these
cuboids contains a volume of 3^ 2 * 1 so
the full shell created here encloses a
volume of 6 * 3^ 2 we can continue this
process as long as we want at each step
we add six copies of a k by K by1 cuboid
alternating between putting two on top
and two on bottom and two on the left
and two on the right when we finally
stop our last stage consists of adding
six copies of an N byn by one cuboid
each of these cuboids contains a volume
of n squ * 1 so the final shell shown
here encloses a volume of 6 * n^ 2 this
process of adding shells at each stage
has built a filled in cuboid whose
volume is given by this finite sum shown
here 6 * 1 2 + 6 * 2^ 2 added all the
way up to 6 * n^ 2 on the other hand
this cuboid has Dimensions n by n + 1 by
2 n + 1 because the final cuboids we
added were n by n by 1 but this means
that the volume of the cuboid is n * n +
1 * 2 n + 1 from this we see that the
finite sum where I ranges from 1 to n of
i^ 2 is n * n + 1 * 2 n + 1 all divided
to recap we've just proved the famous
sum of squares formula by stacking
cuboidal arrays inside of cuboidal
shells as shown here the resulting
formula says that the sum of the first n
squares is equal to n * n + 1 * 2 n + 1
all divided